Finding Aid for Center for Research on Social Organization (University of Michigan)Records, 1960-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Research on Social Organization (University of Michigan)records 1960-2001
University of Michigan. Center for Research on Social Organization.
2 linear feet
03135 Bimu 2
The Center for Research on Social Organization was created in 1960 by the University of Michigan Department of Sociology as a way to centralize and encourage the research and training activities of faculty and graduate students in the area of social organization. The Center's main function is to support the research activities of faculty and students studying organizational arrangements that structure group life, including power relations, distribution of social resources, and historical transformations. The records of the Center reflect its commitment to facilitating faculty and student research on social organization, and includes annual reports, correspondence, committee events, and programs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Center for Research on Social Organization (donor no. 6039 ) in May 2003.
The Center for Research on Social Organization record group are open for research with the exception of restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records - 1 file removed to vault.
The Center for Research on Social Organization (CRSO) was officially established in April 1960, by the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan. The idea for the CRSO arose out of a need by the Department of Sociology to centralize and encourage the research and training activities of faculty and students interested in the area of social organization. Social organization is the analysis of the wide range and variety of organizations and organizational arrangements that structure group life. The principle scholarly concerns are the mutual constitution of power, the distribution of social resources, and historical transformations.
In addition to supporting research in social organization, the CRSO also promotes advanced graduate and postgraduate training in social organization. The CRSO supports research by offering a workspace; access to research equipment and facilities; advice concerning research problems, grants, and administration; contact with other researchers; and a limited amount of secretarial and research assistance.
The Center is administered by a director and administrative assistant. General policies of the CRSO are governed by an executive committee, which consists of the director, administrator, three faculty members elected by the Center faculty and two graduate student representatives elected by the student members of CRSO. Other committees of the CRSO include the facilities committee, which schedules events and is responsible for assigning office space.
The Center is committed to facilitating intellectual exchange and community building among its members. To achieve this goal, CRSO sponsors a variety of intellectual and social activities throughout the year. The two main activities sponsored by the CRSO are the weekly brown bags and the Social Organization Socials. Other events include social organization conferences, the annual cabaret night, and various workshops.
The records of the Center for Research on Social Organization (CRSO) document the history of the Center from its creation in 1960 through 2001. The records are divided into four series: Administrative, Committees, Events and Programs, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Center for Research on Social Organization.; Organizational sociology.; Organization--Research.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; Photographs.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series, 1964-2000 (0.6 linear feet), documents the daily details of running the Center The records included in this series trace the growth and development of the Center. Of particular note are the annual reports covering the activities and projects of the CRSO, changes in faculty, and grant activity.
  - Annual Reports, 1972-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Center Reviews, 1962-1987 (Box 1)
    (scattered)
  - Chairman's Correspondence, 1960-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1997, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial Records, 1974-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
    scattered
  - History of the Center for Research on Social Organizations, 1981-1997 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Move to LS&A Building, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
  - Office Space Applications, 1977-1985 (Box 1)
  - Office Space Assignments, Policy, and Procedure, 1978-1992 (Box 1)
  - Personnel (re: CRSO Directorship), 1987-1997
    [RESTRICTED until July 1, 2027 ]
  - Phone Lists, 1982-1997 (Box 1)
  - Policy Statements, 1976-1998 (Box 1)
  - Small Grant Awards, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - Staff and faculty members, 1980-2000 (Box 1)
  - Visiting Scholars, 1984-1995 (Box 1)
- Committees
  The Committees series, 1978-2001 (0.2 linear feet) documents the work of the Center's Executive Committee and several smaller committees. The Executive Committee is responsible for administering policy. Smaller committees such as, activities and facility committees are responsible for scheduling, assigning facilities, and seeking funding.
  - Committee Responsibilities for Activities, Almanac, Facilities, and Funding Committees, 1978-1996 (Box 1)
  - Computer Committee, 1988-1997 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1987-2001, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Events and Programs
  - Comparative Study of Social Transformations Events, 1987-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Conference on "Labor in the US," November 12-14, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Program in Conflict Management Alternatives, 1987-1995 (Box 2)
  - Events, 1985-2001, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Graduate Student Conferences, 1992-1996 (Box 2)
  - Interdisciplinary Colloquium on Organizational Studies, 1993-1995 (Box 2)
  - Minority Opportunity Summer Training (MOST) Program, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
  - Phoenix Project, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Workshop on Frontiers in Social Movement Theory, June 8-10, 1988 (Box 2)
  - "Zaldfest" Conference, September 17-18, 1999 (Box 2)
    (in honor of Mayer Zald)
- Photographs
  - Robert Cooley Angell, Sociology Professor (Box 2)
  - People and Events, 1990-1997 (Box 2)
  - "As Sociology Meets the World" Conference and Miscellaneous, 1997-2001 (Box 2)
  - "Zaldfest" Conference, September 17-18, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Cabaret 2000, February 5, 2000 (Box 2)